Florence Ellinwood Allen Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Florence Ellinwood Allen Papers 1907-1965
MSS10454
Allen, Florence Ellinwood, 1884-1966
2,700 items 9 containers plus 2 oversize 4 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Judge, feminist, author, and lecturer. Correspondence, speeches, scrapbooks, honors and citations, clippings, photographs, and other papers relating to Allen’s service as an associate justice of the Ohio Supreme Court, her tenure on the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit, and her activities in behalf of women’s rights and peace through international law.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Allen, Florence Ellinwood, 1884-1966.; Astor, Nancy Witcher Langhorne Astor, Viscountess, 1879-1964--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962--Correspondence.; Smith, Margaret Chase, 1897-1995--Correspondence.
Organizations
International Federation of Women Lawyers.; Ohio. Supreme Court.; United States. Court of Appeals (6th Circuit)
Subjects
Courts--Ohio.; International law.; Peace.; Women's rights.
Occupations
Authors.; Feminists.; Jurists.; Lecturers.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Florence Ellinwood Allen were given to the Library of Congress by Allen and by Lamprey Stantial between 1962 and 1965.
Other Repositories
Other papers of Florence Ellinwood Allen can be found at the Schlesinger Library on the History of Women in America, Radcliffe College, Cambridge, Massachusetts.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Florence Ellinwood Allen are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1884, Mar. 23 Born, Salt Lake City, Utah
1904 B.A., Western Reserve University, Cleveland, Ohio
1908 M.A., Western Reserve University, Cleveland, Ohio
1913 LL.B., New York University, New York, N.Y.
1920 Judge, court of common pleas, Cuyahoga County, Ohio
1922-1934 Associate justice, Ohio Supreme Court
1934-1959 Judge, United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit
1940 Published This Constitution of Ours. New York: G. P. Putnam's Sons
1952 Published The Treaty as an Instrument of Legislation. New York: Macmillan
1959-1966 Senior judge, United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit
1965 Published To Do Justly. Cleveland: Press of Western Reserve University
1966, Sept. 12 Died, Waite Hill, Ohio
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Florence Ellinwood Allen (1884-1966) span the period 1907-1965 and relate to her position as associate justice of the Ohio Supreme Court and as judge on the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit. Allen was an active feminist instrumental in obtaining women's suffrage and the first woman to sit on an American court of last resort. She was also the first woman in the United States to occupy the position of senior judge of a federal court of appeals. The papers are organized into the following series: Correspondence, Subject File, Speech and Article File, and Miscellany.
Allen's interest in the women's rights movement is documented by the speeches and articles in her papers. The collection also reveals her interest in the subjects of peace, war, disarmament, and international law. Many of her speeches were delivered to bar associations and subsequently published. Allen received many honorary degrees and the speeches delivered on these occasions are included in the papers.
Approximately half of the collection consists of newspaper clippings pertaining to the judge's activities on behalf of women's suffrage, her campaigns for Congress, consideration of her for a seat on the United States Supreme Court, and honors received in 1959 when she became senior judge of the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit.
Correspondents include Eleanor Roosevelt, Nancy Witcher Langhorne Astor, Viscountess Astor, Margaret Chase Smith, and members of the International Federation of Women Lawyers.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in four series:
Correspondence, 1915-1965
Subject File, 1921-1958
Speech and Article File, 1911-1963
Miscellany, 1907-1959
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm73010454
Container List
- Correspondence, 1915-1965 (Box 1)
  Correspondence.
  Organized into general correspondence, arranged chronologically, and special correspondence, arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization.
  - General, 1915-1965 (Box 1)
  - Special (Box 1)
    - Astor, Nancy Witcher Langhorne, Viscountess Astor, 1929-1955 (Box 1)
    - International Federation of Women Lawyers, 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1948-1959 (Box 1)
    - Smith, Margaret Chase, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
- Subject File, 1921-1958 (Box 1-3)
  Biographical sketches, speeches, book reviews, notes, honors and citations, legal papers, cartoons, newspaper clippings, and other material documenting Allen's activities and interests.
  Arranged by topic or type of material.
  - Biographical (Box 1)
    - Sketches (Box 1)
    - Autobiographical speeches (Box 1)
    - Autobiographical notes (Box 1)
    - Life of Allen and her father (Box 1)
    - Home of Allen (Box 1)
    - Portrait presentation (Box 1)
    - Retirement honors (Box 1)
    - Citations (Box 1)
    - Honorary degrees (Box 1)
    - Margaret Ireland Award (Box 1)
    - Mather College Award, Western Reserve University, Cleveland, Ohio (Box 1)
  - Campaign for United States Senate, 1926 (Box 2)
  - Campaigns for court positions (Box 2)
    - Ohio Supreme Court, 1928 (Box 2)
    - United States Supreme Court, support as first woman, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Conference on Causes and Cures of War (Box 2)
  - International Bar Association, 1948 (Box 2)
  - International Federation of Women Lawyers (Box 2)
    - Japan, 1951 (Box 2)
    - Turkey, 1953 (Box 2)
    - Finland, 1954 (Box 2)
    - United Nations, 1956 (Box 2)
    - Los Angles, Calif., 1958 (Box 2)
  - Legal opinions, index (Box 2)
  - McGannon case, 1921 (Box 2)
  - New York University dinner, New York, N.Y., 1948 (Box 3)
  - Reviews of Allen's books (Box 3)
    - This Constitution of Ours (Box 3)
    - The Treaty as an Instrument of Legislation (Box 3)
  - "This I Believe," radio broadcast, 1942 (Box 3)
  - TVA case, 1937-1938 (Box 3)
  - Woman's suffrage (Box 3)
    - Anthony, Susan B. (Box 3)
    - Donahey, William, cartoons (Box 3)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
    - Notes and research (Box 3)
    - Ohio woman's suffrage (Box 3)
    - Park, Maud Wood, articles (Box 3)
    - Research (Box 3)
    - Shaw, Anna Howard (Box 3)
    - Speech notebook (Box 3)
- Speech and Article File, 1911-1963 (Box 4-5)
  Speeches and articles.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic or title of material.
  - America, speeches, 1924-1957 (Box 4)
  - Anthony, Susan B., 1952 (Box 4)
  - Atomic age, preparing for, 1958 (Box 4)
  - Beloit College, Beloit, Wis., commencement address, 1931 (Box 4)
  - "The Bill of Rights," 1958 (Box 4)
  - "The Bridge to the Future," 1945-1951 (Box 4)
  - Campaign for Congress, 1932 (Box 4)
  - "Challenge to the Citizen," 1960 (Box 4)
  - "Chart for Living," 1953 (Box 4)
  - "The Christian and Government," 1922 (Box 4)
  - The Constitution, speeches (Box 4)
  - Dumbarton Oaks proposals, statement, 1945 (Box 4)
  - "Fair Trial and Freedom of the Press," 1956 (Box 4)
  - Faith (Box 4)
  - Freedom, speeches (Box 4)
  - Gallatin Award, 1960 (Box 4)
  - "The Governmental Task," 1932 (Box 4)
  - Hicks, Xenophon (Box 4)
  - The home, speeches (Box 4)
  - International understanding, article and speech (Box 4)
  - Invention, speech, with reprint, 1958 (Box 4)
  - Jury system, 1930-1954 (Box 4)
  - Justice, 1928-1956 (Box 4)
  - Lake Erie College, Painesville, Ohio, anniversary address, 1948 (Box 4)
  - Law, speeches and writings, 1928-1960 (Box 4)
  - London, England, speeches, 1950 (Box 4)
  - Lyman, Mrs., memorial (Box 4)
  - MacFarlene, Catherine, 1956 (Box 4)
  - "Map for Living," 1957 (Box 4)
  - Mexican trip, lectures (Box 4)
  - Music lectures, 1911 (Box 4)
  - "National and World Planning," 1932 (Box 4)
  - New voters (Box 4)
  - Notes and research (Box 5)
  - New York University, New York, N.Y., reunion dinner, 1963 (Box 5)
  - "The Nuremberg Trial Implements World Law," 1947 (Box 5)
  - "The Outlook," 1931 (Box 5)
  - Patent speech (Box 5)
  - Peace, speeches, 1948-1960 (Box 5)
  - Phi Beta Kappa address, 1934 (Box 5)
  - Recreation, 1934 (Box 5)
  - Sommer, Frank H., 1958 (Box 5)
  - "Taft Watched and Waited" (Box 5)
  - Teachers, address, 1950 (Box 5)
  - Traditions, writings, 1931-1939 (Box 5)
  - Treaties, speeches (Box 5)
  - United Nations Charter and the World Court (Box 5)
  - War, speeches and articles (Box 5)
  - War bonds (Box 5)
  - Washington University in St. Louis, St. Louis, Mo., commencement address, 1955 (Box 5)
  - Women and woman's rights, speeches and articles, 1925-1960 (Box 5)
- Miscellany, 1907-1959 (Box 6-11)
  Photographs, scrapbooks, addresses, newspaper clippings, and other material.
  Arranged by type of material and topic.
  - Photographs (Box 6)
  - Miscellany (Box 6)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 6)
    - Musical interests, 1907-1908 (Box 6)
    - Congressional campaign, 1932 (Box 6)
    - United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit, 1934 (Box 7)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 7)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Newspaper clipping scrapbook (Box 9)
    - Reelection to Ohio Supreme Court, 1928 (Box 9)
    - Current events on the bench, 1931 (Box 9)
  - Congressional campaign, 1932 (Box 10)
  - Addresses (Box 11)